Finding Aid for Eugene H. Leslie Papers, 1916-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eugene H. Leslie Papers 1916-1964
Leslie, Eugene H. (Eugene Hendricks), b. 1892.
85254 Aa 2
Chemical engineer and research scientist, pioneer in the refining of petroleum and synthesis of rubber. Correspondence files, financial records, published research materials; and photograph albums.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
12.3 linear feet
The collection came from the Ann Arbor Department of Parks and Recreation (donor no. 6669 ) and was deposited with the library in two accession in 1981 and 1982.
The collection is open to research.
Eugene H. Leslie was a Professor of Chemical Engineering at the University of Michigan during the 1920's. He left the University in 1928 to become a consulting engineer, working with numerous petroleum refiners and manufacturers in the processing industries and also as an engineering contractor in the sale of complete plants and plant units. He was the owner of Leslie Laboratories, a private research laboratory located in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
Leslie gained his early fame by developing a better process for refining gasoline. He served as consultant for firms building refineries, making White Star Company (the Kennedy-Earhart family of Ann Arbor) an early leader in the field. On the eve of World War II, he became involved in synthetic rubber experimentation, serving as a governmental advisor during the war. He died in 1976, leaving his home, laboratory, and grounds (now Leslie Park Golf Course) to the people of Ann Arbor for recreational purposes.
Summary Contents List
Biographical Material -- Box 1
Alphabetical Correspondence Files, 1916-1964 -- Boxes 1-7
Chronological Correspondence Files (Outgoing), 1924-1958 -- Boxes 7-10
Chronological Correspondence Files, 1933-1952 -- Box 11
Financial Records -- Boxes 11-12
Papers and Reprints, 1920-1927 -- Box 12
Photographs -- Box 12-13
The Eugene H. Leslie Papers collection consists primarily of three series of correspondence: Alphabetical Correspondence Files, 1916-1964; chronological Correspondence Files (Outgoing), 1924-1958; and Chronological Correspondence Files, 1933-1952. There are also three other smaller series: Biographical Material, Financial Records, 1934-1948, and Papers and Reprints, 1920-1927.
Subjects:
Engineering.; Engineers--Michigan.; Leslie, Eugene H. (Eugene Hendricks), b. 1892.; Petroleum industry and trade--United States.; Rubber industry and trade--United States.; Scientists--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agriculture--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Industrial buildings.; Interiors.; Laboratories.; Leslie, Eugene H. (Eugene Hendricks), b. 1892.; Leslie family.; Machinery.; Offices.; Petroleum industry.; Photography.; Railroad cars.; Rubber industry.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Alphabetical Correspondence Files 1916-1964
  - 1916-1920 A-Z
    - American Gas Institute (Box 1)
    - Barneson, Captain John (Box 1)
    - Barneson, Lionel T. (Box 1)
    - Brill, Dr. A. (Box 1)
    - Calvert, Robert P. (Box 1)
    - Chemical Catalogue Company (Box 1)
    - Clary, Edmund B. (Box 1)
    - Crowell, Dr. Will R. (Box 1)
    - Davis, Clark E. (Box 1)
    - Day, Dr. David (Box 1)
    - Derick, Dr. C.G. (Box 1)
    - Dickey, S.J. (Box 1)
    - Fisher, H.L. (Box 1)
    - Garrett, J.P. (Box 1)
    - General Petroleum Company (Box 1)
    - Glany (Box 1)
    - Graham and Harris (Box 1)
    - Leslie, George L. (Box 1)
    - Leslie, Roland R. (Box 1)
    - Moore, T.O. (Box 1)
    - Rittman, Dr. Walter F. (Box 1)
    - Ruby, Irving R. (Box 1)
    - Sawyer, R.C. (Box 1)
    - Security Life Insurance Company (Box 1)
    - Sinclair Refining Company (Box 1)
    - Taber, George H. (Box 1)
    - Tumson, B.R. (Box 1)
    - United States Industrial Alcohol Company (Box 1)
    - Whitaker, M.C. (Box 1)
    - White, Alfred H. (Box 1)
    - Willis, Professor A.R. (Box 1)
    - Young, F.L. (Box 1)
  - 1924-1928 A-Z
    - A (Box 1)
    - Alexander, C.M. (Box 1)
    - American Petroleum Institute (Box 1)
    - American Petroleum Institute (Project 13) (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - Badger (E.B.) and Sons Company
      - Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 1)
      - Boston, Massachusetts (Box 1)
      - Chronological Correspondence 1924-February 1926, 10 folders (Box 1)
      - Chronological Correspondence March 1926-December 1927, 6 folders (Box 2)
      - Peters, W.A., Jr. 1924-1927, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Braun, Carl F. (Box 2)
    - British-American Oil Company (Box 2)
    - C (Box 2)
    - Century Company (Box 2)
    - Chemical Catalogue Company (Box 2)
    - Craig Oil Company (Box 2)
    - Crane Company (Box 2)
    - D (Box 2)
    - E (Box 2)
    - Engineering Research (Box 2)
    - F (Box 2)
    - G (Box 2)
    - Geniesse, J.C. (Box 2)
    - H (Box 2)
    - I (Box 2)
    - Industrial and Engineering Chemistry (Box 2)
    - International Critical Tables (Box 2)
    - J (Box 2)
    - K (Box 2)
    - L (Box 2)
    - M (Box 2)
    - Medvay Oil and Storage (Box 3)
    - Mutual Benefit Life Insurance Company (Box 3)
    - N (Box 3)
    - National Automobile Chamber of Commerce (Box 3)
    - National Research Council (Box 3)
    - O (Box 3)
    - P (Box 3)
    - Paragon Refining Company (Box 3)
    - Phillips Petroleum Company, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Pierce Petroleum Company (Box 3)
    - R (Box 3)
    - Roth Negotiations (Box 3)
    - S (Box 3)
    - Steere Engineering Company (Box 3)
    - Steward and McKay (Box 3)
    - T (Box 3)
    - Truscon Steel Company (Box 3)
    - Tunison, B.R. (Box 3)
    - U (Box 3)
    - United States Government (Box 3)
    - United States Commissioner of Patents (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan (Box 3)
    - V (Box 3)
    - W (Box 3)
    - White Star Refining Company, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1928-1929
    - A-P, 16 folders (Box 4)
    - Q-Z, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - 1928-1933 A-Z
    - Alpha Beta Chapter of the Alpha Chi Sigma Fraternity (Box 4)
    - American Institute of Chemical Engineers (Box 4)
    - American Society for Testing Materials (Box 4)
    - Amtorg Trading Corporation (Box 4)
    - Andrews, John (Box 4)
    - Ashland Refining Company (Box 4)
    - British-American Oil Refineries, Ltd. (Box 4)
    - Coley, Samuel B. (Box 4)
    - Craig Oil Company, Toledo, Ohio (Box 4)
    - Darling and Co. (Box 4)
    - Dorr Company (Box 4)
    - Elk Refining Company (Box 4)
    - Faville, F.A. (Box 4)
    - Freedom Oil Works Company (Earl Craig) (Box 4)
    - Goldtrap, Walter (Box 4)
    - Hammond Iron Works (Box 4)
    - Harper, Buy D. (Box 4)
    - Huron Hills Golf Club (Box 4)
    - Irwin, Bruce (Box 4)
    - Leader Iron Works, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - McKee (Arthur G.) and Company (Box 5)
    - Nixon, Frank H. (Box 5)
    - Old Dutch Refining Company (Box 5)
    - Pennsylvania Refining Company (Box 5)
    - Pennzoil Company (Box 5)
    - Petroleum Engineer (Box 5)
    - Petty, Curtis (Box 5)
    - Petty, Earl (Box 5)
    - Podbielmak, Walter J. (Box 5)
    - Quaker State Oil Refining Company (Box 5)
    - Republic Oil Refining Company (Box 5)
    - Ridgway, Chuck (Box 5)
    - Rittman, Walter F. (Box 5)
    - Shiperovitch, V.L. (Box 5)
    - Struthers-Wells Company (Box 5)
    - Swan Fitch Refining Company (Box 5)
    - Union Iron Works (Box 5)
    - United Refining Company (Box 5)
    - Vacuum Oil Company (Box 5)
    - Valvoline Oil Company (Box 5)
    - Waverly Oil Works Company (Box 5)
    - Wolverine-Empire Refining Company (Box 5)
  - 1930
    - A-Z, 20 folders (Box 5)
  - 1930-1932
    - A-Z, 10 folders (Box 6)
  - 1931-1932
    - A-W, 20 folders (Box 6)
  - 1936-1964
    - 1936, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1937, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 7)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 7)
    - 1942 (Box 7)
    - 1944-1946 (Box 7)
    - 1948-1951 (Box 7)
    - 1952-1954 (Box 7)
    - 1955-1957 (Box 7)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1964 (Box 7)
- Chronological Correspondence Files (Outgoing)
  - September 1924-June 1926, 14 folders (Box 7)
  - July 1926-September 1930, 18 folders (Box 8)
  - October 1930-May 1936, 17 folders (Box 9)
  - June 1936-1952, 17 folders (Box 10)
  - 1958 (Box 10)
- Chronological Correspondence Files
  - 1933-1952, 16 folders (Box 11)
- Financial Records
  - Cash Books and Ledgers 1939-1948 (Box 11)
  - Farm Accounts (Box 12)
- Papers and Reprints
  - 1920-1927, 3 folders (Box 12)
- Photographs
  - Blaw-Knox Co., Pittsburgh, PA.
    - Equipment. Photograph Nos. B5707-B6282 April 1939-September 1940 (Box 12)
    - Equipment. Photograph Nos. B6374-B6811 January 1941-March 1942 (Box 12)
    - Equipment. Photograph Nos. B6551-B6555 and B6606 (Methyl-ethyl-Ketone Plant, B.F. Goodrich Co., Akron, OH.,) May 1941, October 1941 (Box 12)
    - Offices and Personnel 1940-1942 (Box 12)
  - Family and friends, early photographs (Box 12)
  - Family and friends, later photographs (Box 12)
    (including photography pictures)
  - Farming experiments (Box 12)
  - Groups-Unidentified (Box 12)
  - Homes: Ann Arbor, Michigan and Ottawa, Illinois [Leslie Labs] (Box 12)
  - Laboratories. (Box 12)
    (See also Homes)
  - Oil Industry
    - Acetic Acid Plant, East Ohio Gas Co. 1939 (Box 12)
    - Cracking Stills, ca. 1920s (Box 12)
    - Dubbs Process. (Box 12)
    - Equipment (Box 12)
    - Oil Wells (Box 12)
    - Pennsylvania. (Box 12)
    - Refineries, Identified: California, Pennsylvania, Toronto (Box 12)
    - Refineries, Identified: Texas, Wyoming, Louisiana, Arkansas, Oklahoma, Iran, South America. Includes Skelly and Shell Oil Co. (Box 12)
    - Refineries, Identified: White Star Refining Co., Wood River (Box 12)
    - Refineries, Unidentified (Box 12)
  - Portraits and snapshots (Box 12)
  - Railroad Cars (Box 12)
  - Travel (Box 12)
  - Albums, 2 volumes (Box 13)
    (include oil industry photographs)